<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Owlbadger on OwlBadger</title><link>owlbadger.com/</link><description>Recent content in Owlbadger on OwlBadger</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-uk</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="owlbadger.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>About</title><link>owlbadger.com/top/about/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>owlbadger.com/top/about/</guid><description>&lt;p>I have no idea, it was just a spare domain I had lying around.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So I found myself discussing music a lot on the book of faces, and thought to myself, “why am I feeding the beast with content when I could have my own little space on the web?” So here it is, Owlbadger, where I can exhibit my unabashed opinions about music, books, or anthing else that takes my fancy.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Decadent Herbs</title><link>owlbadger.com/posts/2020-09-16-the-decadent-herbs/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>owlbadger.com/posts/2020-09-16-the-decadent-herbs/</guid><description>&lt;p>It was 1985, I was twenty years old and just back from nine months volunteering in India. I&amp;rsquo;d decided not to go to university, but instead to try my luck as a rock star, all I needed was a band.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At first I tried answering adds in the musicians wanted section of Melody Maker, I must have sent off several applications, but only got one audition with a very odd band from South London with a female vocalist who screamed over a monotonous bass and drums. They wanted a flamenco guitar to go with it, and I was plainly not suitable. So that summer I sat around at St. Julians getting a little bored and not really knowing what to do with myself.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The OwlBadger Guide to Yes</title><link>owlbadger.com/posts/2019-12-29-yes-3/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>owlbadger.com/posts/2019-12-29-yes-3/</guid><description>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="../2019-10-19-yes-1">Part 1. Introduction and Early Albums&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="../2019-10-31-yes-2">Part 2. Early Classic Period&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Part 3. Late Classic Period &lt;em>which you are now reading&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This is the third part of the Owlbadger guide to Yes. It covers, what I’m calling their ‘late classic period’, the albums: Tales From Topographic Oceans, Relayer, and Going For The One. This period is far more patchy in terms of quality than the &amp;rsquo;early classic period&amp;rsquo;, but features two Yes masterpieces that cannot be missed and much other music that any Yes fan will enjoy.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The OwlBadger Guide to Yes</title><link>owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-31-yes-2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-31-yes-2/</guid><description>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="../2019-10-19-yes-1">Part 1. Introduction and Early Albums&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Part 2. Early Classic Period &lt;em>which you are now reading&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="../2019-12-29-yes-3">Part 3. Late Classic Period&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This is the second part of the Owlbadger guide to Yes. It covers, what I’m calling their ‘early classic period’, the albums: The Yes Album, Fragile, Close to the Edge and Yessongs. This is when the band produced much of their best work. The output of these albums is consistently excellent, especially compared with the more patchy ‘late classic’ period that we will be looking at next.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The OwlBadger Guide to Yes</title><link>owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-19-yes-1/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-19-yes-1/</guid><description>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Part 1. Introduction and Early Albums &lt;em>which you are now reading&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="../2019-10-31-yes-2">Part 2. Early Classic Period&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="../2019-12-29-yes-3">Part 3. Late Classic Period&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This is the first in a series of Owlbadger guides, where we look at the work of one band or artist with a critical and opinionated eye. The idea is that someone unfamiliar with their work has an insight into where to start, what to spend time on and, more importantly, what to ignore; this is information that’s difficult to glean from an impartial source such as Wikipedia and is especially important with a band such as Yes, with a career spanning decades and an output that ranges dramatically in style and quality. There’s the added complication that some of their most commercially successful work is music that Owlbadger fans will heartily dislike. It’s easy to be mislead into thinking that Yes are simply awful 80’s MOR if all you’ve heard is ‘Owner of a Lonely Heart’, and that would be a great shame because, as I hope to show, Yes music from their early to mid 70’s era is one of the most glorious artifacts of the golden age of rock.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Awaken My Love!</title><link>owlbadger.com/posts/2018-07-09-awaken-my-love/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>owlbadger.com/posts/2018-07-09-awaken-my-love/</guid><description>&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Awaken, My Love!&amp;rdquo; is the 2016 studio album by Donald Glover, under his stage name Childish Gambino. A modern take on 70’s psychedelic funk and somewhat of a Prince tribute, it manages to combine crowd pleasing melodies with some quite messy left-field experimentation making it one of the more interesting records of the last few years.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was introduced to AWL by my 15 year old son. I’m almost completely unaware of modern rap and R&amp;amp;B music, which I mostly find very hard to connect with. I’m sure there’s some excellent stuff out there, but mostly it’s not really my thing. I doubt that I would have stumbled across AWL if left to my own devices, so thanks Leo! It just helps to reinforce my belief that there’s probably huge amounts of great music out there that I’d really love if only I knew where to find it, and that the main challenge for the music industry in the 2010’s is discovery. In an ideal world there would be someone on the internet with musical taste identical to my own, but who spends 12 hours a day listening to music and discovering all the wonderful things I might like. Alas I’ve yet to find them - another discovery problem.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Aristocrats</title><link>owlbadger.com/posts/2018-05-23-the-aristocrats/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>owlbadger.com/posts/2018-05-23-the-aristocrats/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is the 2011 self named debut album of instrumental supergroup The Aristocrats. A textbook exercise in instrumental rock. No overdubs, just virtuoso guitar, bass and drums playing fusion infused rock.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Aristocrats is a band platform designed to show off the musical talents of Guthrie Govan on guitar, Bryan Beller on bass, and Marco Minnemann on drums. Each of them a well known and respected session player in their own right before coming together for this band. It’s a collection of nine tracks, three each supplied by each player. Because Beller’s bass has a very bassy tone (yes, that’s right), with hardly any high end, it’s Govan’s guitar that takes up the majority of the audio spectrum and does the main job of carrying the music. No overdubs means that you’re really just listening to an hour of a single guitar player supported by a world class rhythm section. It’s a tribute to Govan’s incredible ability and imagination that he pulls it off. I’m a great admirer of his tone, slightly distorted with much twang and articulation, rather than the over compressed and saturated tone of most contemporary shredders. This is not to denigrate the other two musicians, Minnemann’s ability to follow every twist and turn of Govan’s formidable playing is quite remarkable, while Beller plays an excellent supporting role. I suppose my only real disappointment is that his tone is so low that it leaves the bass line somewhat indistinct. It would have been nice to have him a little more Chris Squire, if you know what I mean. The production is just as it should be for this kind of album: transparent. If you noticed it, it would be wrong.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Flying Microtonal Banana</title><link>owlbadger.com/posts/2018-05-04-fmb/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>owlbadger.com/posts/2018-05-04-fmb/</guid><description>&lt;p>Flying Microtonal Banana is the ninth studio album by Melbourne psych rockers King Gizzard and the Lizard Wizard. Released in 2017 as part of their five albums in one year project, it’s a psychedelic masterpiece of driving rhythms and exotic eastern melodies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can’t accuse King Gizzard of being lazy psyched out bums. Their ambition to record five albums in one year, declared at the beginning of 2017, shows huge ambition and a pretty full-on work ethic. It’s not as if they spent the year in the studio either, the five albums were recorded in between international tours. The other expectation from a band putting out such a huge quantity of music is that quality would suffer, but that’s surprisingly not at all the case. Not only are each of 2017’s Gizzard releases great records in their own right, but even more impressively, each one has a very distinct sound and vision. Flying Microtonal Banana is the first of the five, and the one that adheres most closely to the psychedelic rock label, but with an eccentric twist.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Dojo</title><link>owlbadger.com/posts/2018-04-28-dojo/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>owlbadger.com/posts/2018-04-28-dojo/</guid><description>&lt;p>Dojo is the debut album by Jouis, Brighton based graduates of the local BIMM music school (the name is a French word that translates roughly to &amp;ldquo;High enjoyment&amp;rdquo;, apparently). A quintet when the album was recorded in 2015, and now a trio. It is a wholly undiscovered gem of a record, full of immersive, laid back, progressive vibes, and probably my favorite album of 2016.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I first encountered JOUIS purely by accident. Taken by a friend to watch a Syd Arthur gig at the Komedia in Brighton, JOUIS were the support band. I was completely blown away. Along with around just 50 other people I experienced one of my most enjoyable gigs of recent years. I immediately went online to find out more and discovered that they’d recently released this album which soon found an almost permanent place on my regular playlist. Since then I’ve discovered that several of my acquaintances know them personally, so I’ve started to feel a slight one-degree-of-separation connection with them. It’s so nice in any case that one of my favorite bands are both local and current.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Do Hollywood</title><link>owlbadger.com/posts/2018-04-25-do-hollywood/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>owlbadger.com/posts/2018-04-25-do-hollywood/</guid><description>&lt;p>Released in October 2016, this is the debut album by the Lemon Twigs. The creation of the teenage D’Addario brothers, Brian and Michael, it’s a work of quite astonishing precociousness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Influences from the classic past of pop and rock run strongly throughout the record, but it’s not a pastiche; the inspiration is obvious but the execution is unique and creative. Possibly being so young and unhindered by any thoughts of what they should be doing, they’ve entirely indulged themselves, throwing whatever sounded right into a richly textured matrix. It’s quirky, boy is it quirky, abrupt changes of key and pace, surprising little songwriting twists that wouldn’t be allowed in any grownup record abound. Like a Monty Python sketch, where they’ve suddenly thought, “OK, this is getting boring now, let’s just stop here and do something completely different.” they transition swiftly and skillfully between radically different sections. It’s all done with such skill and poise that it’s not at all jarring, just delightful. Surprise is a key ingredient in all great music and the D’Addario brothers supply it in abundance.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Seal St. Lawrence</title><link>owlbadger.com/posts/2012-01-06-seal-st-lawrence/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>owlbadger.com/posts/2012-01-06-seal-st-lawrence/</guid><description>&lt;p>Seal St. Lawrence was my primary school, a tiny church of England school attached to the parish church.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Both were built in 1865 by Horace Wilkinson to commemorate his daughter. The building itself looked like a large victorian house facing a tarmac playground. Opposite the school building was a world war two air raid shelter. I vaguely remember it being used for storage. Around the back of the building was a garden which we were expressly forbidden to enter. Across the road was some woodland and then the sports field. We were allowed to play in the woodland during the lunchtime break, it seemed huge to me as a small boy. I remember kicking large mounds of fallen leaves around and endless games of British Bulldog. The playing fields had a football pitch with a running track around it and there were some apparatus on the far side including a frame with ropes, that I never managed to climb to the top of.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>