<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Owlbadger on OwlBadger</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/</link><description>Recent content in Owlbadger on OwlBadger</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-uk</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://owlbadger.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>About</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/top/about/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/top/about/</guid><description>&lt;p>I have no idea, it was just a spare domain I had lying around.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So I found myself discussing music a lot on the book of faces, and thought to myself, “why am I feeding the beast with content when I could have my own little space on the web?” So here it is, Owlbadger, where I can exhibit my unabashed opinions about music, books, or anthing else that takes my fancy.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Book Review: Memoirs of a Georgian Rake</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2025-03-05-hickey-rake/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2025-03-05-hickey-rake/</guid><description>&lt;p>William Hickey, born in 1749 into Anglo-Irish gentry, lived through the height of the Georgian renaissance during the reign of George III. Although his profession was that of an attorney, his real passion in life was fast living. Especially, as a young man, partying, drinking, and women. Lots of women. The memoirs are very touching, because he constantly laments his bad behaviour, and especially the disappointment of his beloved father, but he simply can’t stop himself from “dissipation”; constantly falling in with the worst kind of company, and he can never turn down a professional lady. Some his excesses are hilariously funny, such as the time his sisters dressed him as a nun and then took him to a party where he became abominably drunk and raucous, while the wits around him tut-tutted at such bad behaviour from a lady of God. It’s a superb insight into the underside of Georgian London, and the life that could be had if one had a little money, the right friends, and avoided the ubiquitous STDs. Hickey, after several failed attempts, finally finds fortune practicing as an attorney in Bengal with the East India Company. He returns to London, where he spends the fortune over several years, then returns to India with his wife Charlotte on an 18 month voyage from hell, which features them nearly shipwrecked in a monsoon hurricane, and then captured by the French. It’s notable how large a part of the memoirs are devoted to life at sea. Poor Charlotte died soon after arriving in Calcutta, and Hickey then took up with an Indian women who later also died, this time from childbirth. He eventually retired at age 58 and returned to England where he settled quietly in Buckinghamshire for the next two decades until his death in 1830. He doesn’t comment much at all on Indian culture, and appears to take little interest in it, which is a shame. The Indian sections of the book are in many ways the least interesting. It’s the debauched living in London that’s the real treat, and that make this volume such a classic.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Decadent Herbs</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2020-09-16-the-decadent-herbs/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2020-09-16-the-decadent-herbs/</guid><description>&lt;p>It was 1985, I was twenty years old and just back from nine months volunteering in India. I&amp;rsquo;d decided not to go to university, but instead to try my luck as a rock star, all I needed was a band.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The OwlBadger Guide to Yes</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-12-29-yes-3/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-12-29-yes-3/</guid><description>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-19-yes-1/">Part 1. Introduction and Early Albums&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-31-yes-2/">Part 2. Early Classic Period&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Part 3. Late Classic Period &lt;em>which you are now reading&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This is the third part of the Owlbadger guide to Yes. It covers, what I’m calling their ‘late classic period’, the albums: Tales From Topographic Oceans, Relayer, and Going For The One. This period is far more patchy in terms of quality than the &amp;rsquo;early classic period&amp;rsquo;, but features two Yes masterpieces that cannot be missed and much other music that any Yes fan will enjoy.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The OwlBadger Guide to Yes</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-31-yes-2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-31-yes-2/</guid><description>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-19-yes-1/">Part 1. Introduction and Early Albums&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Part 2. Early Classic Period &lt;em>which you are now reading&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-12-29-yes-3/">Part 3. Late Classic Period&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This is the second part of the Owlbadger guide to Yes. It covers, what I’m calling their ‘early classic period’, the albums: The Yes Album, Fragile, Close to the Edge and Yessongs. This is when the band produced much of their best work. The output of these albums is consistently excellent, especially compared with the more patchy ‘late classic’ period that we will be looking at next.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The OwlBadger Guide to Yes</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-19-yes-1/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-19-yes-1/</guid><description>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Part 1. Introduction and Early Albums &lt;em>which you are now reading&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-31-yes-2/">Part 2. Early Classic Period&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-12-29-yes-3/">Part 3. Late Classic Period&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This is the first in a series of Owlbadger guides, where we look at the work of one band or artist with a critical and opinionated eye. The idea is that someone unfamiliar with their work has an insight into where to start, what to spend time on and, more importantly, what to ignore; this is information that’s difficult to glean from an impartial source such as Wikipedia and is especially important with a band such as Yes, with a career spanning decades and an output that ranges dramatically in style and quality. There’s the added complication that some of their most commercially successful work is music that Owlbadger fans will heartily dislike. It’s easy to be mislead into thinking that Yes are simply awful 80’s MOR if all you’ve heard is ‘Owner of a Lonely Heart’, and that would be a great shame because, as I hope to show, Yes music from their early to mid 70’s era is one of the most glorious artifacts of the golden age of rock.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Awaken My Love!</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-07-09-awaken-my-love/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-07-09-awaken-my-love/</guid><description>&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Awaken, My Love!&amp;rdquo; is the 2016 studio album by Donald Glover, under his stage name Childish Gambino. A modern take on 70’s psychedelic funk and somewhat of a Prince tribute, it manages to combine crowd pleasing melodies with some quite messy left-field experimentation making it one of the more interesting records of the last few years.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Aristocrats</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-05-23-the-aristocrats/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-05-23-the-aristocrats/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is the 2011 self named debut album of instrumental supergroup The Aristocrats. A textbook exercise in instrumental rock. No overdubs, just virtuoso guitar, bass and drums playing fusion infused rock.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Flying Microtonal Banana</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-05-04-fmb/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-05-04-fmb/</guid><description>&lt;p>Flying Microtonal Banana is the ninth studio album by Melbourne psych rockers King Gizzard and the Lizard Wizard. Released in 2017 as part of their five albums in one year project, it’s a psychedelic masterpiece of driving rhythms and exotic eastern melodies.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Dojo</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-04-28-dojo/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-04-28-dojo/</guid><description>&lt;p>Dojo is the debut album by Jouis, Brighton based graduates of the local BIMM music school (the name is a French word that translates roughly to &amp;ldquo;High enjoyment&amp;rdquo;, apparently). A quintet when the album was recorded in 2015, and now a trio. It is a wholly undiscovered gem of a record, full of immersive, laid back, progressive vibes, and probably my favorite album of 2016.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Do Hollywood</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-04-25-do-hollywood/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-04-25-do-hollywood/</guid><description>&lt;p>Released in October 2016, this is the debut album by the Lemon Twigs. The creation of the teenage D’Addario brothers, Brian and Michael, it’s a work of quite astonishing precociousness.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Seal St. Lawrence</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2012-01-06-seal-st-lawrence/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2012-01-06-seal-st-lawrence/</guid><description>&lt;p>Seal St. Lawrence was my primary school, a tiny church of England school attached to the parish church.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Both were built in 1865 by Horace Wilkinson to commemorate his daughter. The building itself looked like a large victorian house facing a tarmac playground. Opposite the school building was a world war two air raid shelter. I vaguely remember it being used for storage. Around the back of the building was a garden which we were expressly forbidden to enter. Across the road was some woodland and then the sports field. We were allowed to play in the woodland during the lunchtime break, it seemed huge to me as a small boy. I remember kicking large mounds of fallen leaves around and endless games of British Bulldog. The playing fields had a football pitch with a running track around it and there were some apparatus on the far side including a frame with ropes, that I never managed to climb to the top of.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>