<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Book on OwlBadger</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/tags/book/</link><description>Recent content in Book on OwlBadger</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-uk</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://owlbadger.com/tags/book/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Book Review: Great Uncle Harry</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2025-04-15-palin-harry/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2025-04-15-palin-harry/</guid><description>&lt;p>This was a very light and entertaining little book. I finished it in just four days, which might be a record. Palin is, as you’d expect, an excellent and engaging writer, and he effortlessly relates the life of his Edwardian ancestor. It’s indeed fascinating to follow the journey of a very ordinary man thrust in extraordinary events; from his time as a trainee clerk on Indian Railways at the hight of the British Empire, and then as failed junior manager in the Assam tea plantations. He seems to have finally settled down as a farmhand in New Zeeland for a couple of years before being caught up in WWI, joining the NZ army and seeing action, first in Gallipoli, where he was lucky to survive, then in France, and finally the battle of the Somme, where his luck ran out. Born into a wealthy and prosperous family and given a public school education. He had every opportunity in life. The fact that he failed in India, and then wound up as a farm hand in NZ, leads one to suspect that his Indian foreman was correct when he described him as “lacking intelligence”. Only after several years of army service did he rise above the rank of private and become a lance corporal. His diary entries, which form the backbone of the book are very basic lists of letters arriving and his movements from place to place. There’s almost no reflection or contemplation of what it all meant. Palin has to turn to other diarists who were present at the time to fill out the details. There seems to be something of Forest Gump about him however, in that he stoically endures the hardships of war in Turkey and France, with little complaint, and seems to have made an excellent soldier. Palin’s description of his final movements in the Somme leading up to his death are very moving. It must have been quite dramatic to finally discover the field where one’s great uncle lost his life to a German bullet.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Book Review: Catatrosphe</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2025-04-10-hastings-catastrophe/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2025-04-10-hastings-catastrophe/</guid><description>&lt;p>Published in 2014 on the 100th anniversary of the beginning of WWI, this is Max Hastings’ overview of the beginning of WWI from the assassination of Franz Ferdinand to the first Christmas of the war at the end of 1914. This was one of the volumes I picked from my grandfather John’s bookshelf after he died. His father, my great-grandfather, fought in WWI on the Western Front. I have his campaign medals. So there’s a family connection with the story. Hastings’ is a prolific historian of 20th C. war. I’ve read several of his books before. He writes in an engaging style, explaining grand strategy and the wide sweep of events, while at the same time weaving in individual lives and their personal reactions from being swept up by war. It is truly a terrible tale of unimaginable hubris and folly on the part of the statesmen who willed the war to happen. Hastings is in no doubt that the blame lies fully with first the Austrians for kicking the whole thing off, and then very much the Germans for both cheering them on and then launching their own attack on France. He’s dismissive of view that Britain should have stayed out of it, saying that it would have been very bad for Britain to have a continent dominated by an aggressively militaristic Germany. Of course, without being able to re-run history we’ll never know. On the battlefield it’s clear that nobody expected that the modern technologies of machine guns and long-range high-explosive artillery would give defenders such a huge advantage, and that the front would inevitably congeal into a bloody, muddy, killing machine that simply ground up soldiers by the thousands. It’s a testament to human resilience that most were able to endure it. The contrast between the jingoistic celebration by many at the outbreak, and the grim desperate reality of the trenches is stark. A lesson for all times. War is never glamorous or glorious, but sometimes must be endured.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Book Review: Memoirs of a Georgian Rake</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2025-03-05-hickey-rake/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2025-03-05-hickey-rake/</guid><description>&lt;p>William Hickey, born in 1749 into Anglo-Irish gentry, lived through the height of the Georgian renaissance during the reign of George III. Although his profession was that of an attorney, his real passion in life was fast living. Especially, as a young man, partying, drinking, and women. Lots of women. The memoirs are very touching, because he constantly laments his bad behaviour, and especially the disappointment of his beloved father, but he simply can’t stop himself from “dissipation”; constantly falling in with the worst kind of company, and he can never turn down a professional lady. Some his excesses are hilariously funny, such as the time his sisters dressed him as a nun and then took him to a party where he became abominably drunk and raucous, while the wits around him tut-tutted at such bad behaviour from a lady of God. It’s a superb insight into the underside of Georgian London, and the life that could be had if one had a little money, the right friends, and avoided the ubiquitous STDs. Hickey, after several failed attempts, finally finds fortune practicing as an attorney in Bengal with the East India Company. He returns to London, where he spends the fortune over several years, then returns to India with his wife Charlotte on an 18 month voyage from hell, which features them nearly shipwrecked in a monsoon hurricane, and then captured by the French. It’s notable how large a part of the memoirs are devoted to life at sea. Poor Charlotte died soon after arriving in Calcutta, and Hickey then took up with an Indian women who later also died, this time from childbirth. He eventually retired at age 58 and returned to England where he settled quietly in Buckinghamshire for the next two decades until his death in 1830. He doesn’t comment much at all on Indian culture, and appears to take little interest in it, which is a shame. The Indian sections of the book are in many ways the least interesting. It’s the debauched living in London that’s the real treat, and that make this volume such a classic.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Book Review: Who We Are And How We Got Here</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-10-20-reich-who/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-10-20-reich-who/</guid><description>&lt;p>The book describes the revolution currently taking place in archeology thanks to the technology of ancient DNA sampling. It reveals a rich pattern of human dispersal and mixing over the past 100,000 years. In the very distant past it shows that there was interbreeding with Neaderthals and Denisovans, making us non-Africans something of a hybrid. There’s even some suggestion that Eurasian features like lighter skin might be inherited from them. In the more recent past it clears up some archeological disputes about whether cultural change in the archeological record is due to copying or population movement. It seems it’s almost always the latter. Also differences in Y-chromosome and mitochondrial DNA ancestry shows that in many cases males from the incoming population mated with females from the existing one. This is especially true of the Yamnaya people of the central European steppe who spread into northern Europe and South Asia around 4,000 years ago bringing indo-European languages, horses, and the wheel. It really is incredible to think of all the people struggling to survive over millennium, moving from place to place and fighting each other for dominance. How we are all the descents of a long line of survivors. Reich writes very well. It’s a very practical book that lays out the discoveries in a matter-of-fact style. He’s obviously very touchy about any association with theories of racial superiority, and explains at length how his discoveries do not support some of the more lurid online claims made about them. I thought his appeal to liberal ideas about individual equality regardless of one’s genetic inheritance was very good, and an excellent antidote to both right-wing racial supremacists and woke identity politics. This is a very exciting field. Reich describes how we might soon see a complete historical atlas of human movement and evolution. I expect he’ll have to write another book in a few years time with the updates.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>