<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on OwlBadger</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on OwlBadger</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-uk</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://owlbadger.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Great Uncle Harry</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2025-04-15-palin-harry/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2025-04-15-palin-harry/</guid><description>&lt;p>This was a very light and entertaining little book. I finished it in just four days, which might be a record. Palin is, as you’d expect, an excellent and engaging writer, and he effortlessly relates the life of his Edwardian ancestor. It’s indeed fascinating to follow the journey of a very ordinary man thrust in extraordinary events; from his time as a trainee clerk on Indian Railways at the hight of the British Empire, and then as failed junior manager in the Assam tea plantations. He seems to have finally settled down as a farmhand in New Zeeland for a couple of years before being caught up in WWI, joining the NZ army and seeing action, first in Gallipoli, where he was lucky to survive, then in France, and finally the battle of the Somme, where his luck ran out. Born into a wealthy and prosperous family and given a public school education. He had every opportunity in life. The fact that he failed in India, and then wound up as a farm hand in NZ, leads one to suspect that his Indian foreman was correct when he described him as “lacking intelligence”. Only after several years of army service did he rise above the rank of private and become a lance corporal. His diary entries, which form the backbone of the book are very basic lists of letters arriving and his movements from place to place. There’s almost no reflection or contemplation of what it all meant. Palin has to turn to other diarists who were present at the time to fill out the details. There seems to be something of Forest Gump about him however, in that he stoically endures the hardships of war in Turkey and France, with little complaint, and seems to have made an excellent soldier. Palin’s description of his final movements in the Somme leading up to his death are very moving. It must have been quite dramatic to finally discover the field where one’s great uncle lost his life to a German bullet.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Catatrosphe</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2025-04-10-hastings-catastrophe/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2025-04-10-hastings-catastrophe/</guid><description>&lt;p>Published in 2014 on the 100th anniversary of the beginning of WWI, this is Max Hastings’ overview of the beginning of WWI from the assassination of Franz Ferdinand to the first Christmas of the war at the end of 1914. This was one of the volumes I picked from my grandfather John’s bookshelf after he died. His father, my great-grandfather, fought in WWI on the Western Front. I have his campaign medals. So there’s a family connection with the story. Hastings’ is a prolific historian of 20th C. war. I’ve read several of his books before. He writes in an engaging style, explaining grand strategy and the wide sweep of events, while at the same time weaving in individual lives and their personal reactions from being swept up by war. It is truly a terrible tale of unimaginable hubris and folly on the part of the statesmen who willed the war to happen. Hastings is in no doubt that the blame lies fully with first the Austrians for kicking the whole thing off, and then very much the Germans for both cheering them on and then launching their own attack on France. He’s dismissive of view that Britain should have stayed out of it, saying that it would have been very bad for Britain to have a continent dominated by an aggressively militaristic Germany. Of course, without being able to re-run history we’ll never know. On the battlefield it’s clear that nobody expected that the modern technologies of machine guns and long-range high-explosive artillery would give defenders such a huge advantage, and that the front would inevitably congeal into a bloody, muddy, killing machine that simply ground up soldiers by the thousands. It’s a testament to human resilience that most were able to endure it. The contrast between the jingoistic celebration by many at the outbreak, and the grim desperate reality of the trenches is stark. A lesson for all times. War is never glamorous or glorious, but sometimes must be endured.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Memoirs of a Georgian Rake</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2025-03-05-hickey-rake/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2025-03-05-hickey-rake/</guid><description>&lt;p>William Hickey, born in 1749 into Anglo-Irish gentry, lived through the height of the Georgian renaissance during the reign of George III. Although his profession was that of an attorney, his real passion in life was fast living. Especially, as a young man, partying, drinking, and women. Lots of women. The memoirs are very touching, because he constantly laments his bad behaviour, and especially the disappointment of his beloved father, but he simply can’t stop himself from “dissipation”; constantly falling in with the worst kind of company, and he can never turn down a professional lady. Some his excesses are hilariously funny, such as the time his sisters dressed him as a nun and then took him to a party where he became abominably drunk and raucous, while the wits around him tut-tutted at such bad behaviour from a lady of God. It’s a superb insight into the underside of Georgian London, and the life that could be had if one had a little money, the right friends, and avoided the ubiquitous STDs. Hickey, after several failed attempts, finally finds fortune practicing as an attorney in Bengal with the East India Company. He returns to London, where he spends the fortune over several years, then returns to India with his wife Charlotte on an 18 month voyage from hell, which features them nearly shipwrecked in a monsoon hurricane, and then captured by the French. It’s notable how large a part of the memoirs are devoted to life at sea. Poor Charlotte died soon after arriving in Calcutta, and Hickey then took up with an Indian women who later also died, this time from childbirth. He eventually retired at age 58 and returned to England where he settled quietly in Buckinghamshire for the next two decades until his death in 1830. He doesn’t comment much at all on Indian culture, and appears to take little interest in it, which is a shame. The Indian sections of the book are in many ways the least interesting. It’s the debauched living in London that’s the real treat, and that make this volume such a classic.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>George III</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2025-02-07-roberts-george/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2025-02-07-roberts-george/</guid><description>&lt;p>I read Andrew Roberts’ biography of Churchill a few years ago which I very much enjoyed. This similar sized book on George III is just as readable and interesting, and very much a education for me because I know relatively little about the history of the late 18th C. George’s reign stretched from 1760 to 1820, but he was incapacitated for much of the last 10 years, so the core of the book deals with his active engagement with events between 1760 and 1810. The two major historical events of this time were the American war of independence followed by the French revolution and Napoleonic era. It’s George’s reputation in the United States as a inhumane tyrant that Roberts is most keen to revise. He makes a very good case that George was the opposite; humane, educated, and most importantly a stickler for the English constitution and the place of parliament. One of the most interesting aspects of the book is the light it shines on the gradual withdrawal of the monarch from executive power during George’s reign, and the consolidation of the prime minister as the lead political actor in the British system. Roberts writes very well and there are some very entertaining moments, such as a very funny line on an MP called George Gordon, a well known libertine, who had called the Archbishop of Canterbury ‘The Whore of Babylon’. “A wit commented that Gordon had finally met a whore he didn’t like”. One of the tragedies of the story is George’s opposition to catholic emancipation, which if it had been enacted would have allowed Ireland to become an equal member of the united kingdom. Instead the exclusion of much of the population from public life simply fermented resentment of the English, which only worsened throughout the rest of the 19th C. and lead to the tragic civil war and partition. One would have thought that the British establishment might have learnt something from the American independence movement and acted to re-empt separatist sentiment by giving ground early. Unfortunately not. The book gives lots of anecdotal flavour of the late 18th C. and I’m eager to read more about that era. I might try Andrew Roberts’ own Napoleon biography in the near future. All in all an excellent read. I’m very glad I made time for it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>End Times</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-12-02-turchin-end/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-12-02-turchin-end/</guid><description>&lt;p>Peter Turchin is the founder of a new kind of scientific history named “cliodynamics”. He and his team have collected a vast database of historical data: on populations, economic statistics, epidemics, laws, and heath data. It covers most of the world over an extended time period. From this he derives testable scientific theories about history. The focus of this book is his theory of “elite overproduction and popular immiseration”, which says that throughout history there is a tendency for elites to extract ever more surplus from the working class, which becomes immiserated in the process, while the elite expands until there too many “elite candidates” for the elite roles on offer. The frustrated aspirants then mobilise the immiserated and ripe-for-revolution masses to destabilise the state and cause a collapse. This slims down the size of the elite, and often the population as a whole and allows the cycle to repeat itself. In pre-industrial societies the cycle is Malthusian, with over population leading to famines and epidemics that cull the numbers, but in the modern era he says the mechanism is the strength of the “wealth pump”, and how efficiently it pumps wealth to the elite. The book focuses on the USA, which he thinks is now due a revolution or civil war. Prescient with Trump returning to the Whitehouse. Do I buy it? He makes a very persuasive case, especially for pre-industrial societies, but I’m not so convinced about his diagnosis of the US. His model fails to account for business innovation and the overall growth of the economic pie. He only cares how it’s cut. While he admires Denmark and Austria, they are hardly engines of world economic growth like the US. It’s all a bit too Marxist for me. I do think the idea of “elite overproduction” is a useful one though. Who knows whether his predictions about the future of the US turn out to be true. I rather hope not because they are quite apocalyptic!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Queen As It Began</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-11-21-smith-queen/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-11-21-smith-queen/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is probably one of most badly written books I’ve read in a very long time. It’s only because I wanted to know the history of the band that I stuck with it. It’s not just badly written, but it’s also a fawning hagiography, that feels more like a vapid press release from Brian May’s office than critical and intelligent assessment of the band. On the one hand there’s too much detail; almost every gig and recording session is listed, but without any critical assessment. There’s nothing about the music, or what the band members thought of the music, or any disagreements they might have had. The characterisation of the main players is cardboard; you don’t get any sense of them as fully rounded people. There’s so much rock star excess and ego ignored. It would have made for a fantastic story if only the authors had the guts to tell it. If only Queen had a Philip Norman or Ian Leslie to write about them. I guess my own assessment of them as a band hasn’t changed, I still think they were one of the most talented group of musicians ever to come together, who made four excellent, world class, rock albums up to A Night At The Opera, but then settled into a rut of releasing perfectly crafted top 10 singles along with uninspired and mostly filler albums.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Twenty-One Tales</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-11-12-kipling-tales/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-11-12-kipling-tales/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is a very attractive Folio Society volume of Kipling short stories that span his entire career. It one of the many Folio volumes that I’ve recently liberated from my late Dad’s collection. I don’t think I’ve ever read anything of Kipling’s before, which is an oversight, since he’s one of Sussex’s most famous authors, and I’ve been to his house, Batemans, many times. Half of the stories, and Kipling’s career, are set in the India of the British Raj, and are the most colourful, exotic, and historically interesting. The Man Who Would Be King is of course the most famous of these, a glorious tale of imperial entrepreneurship and hubris. But there’s also Without Benefit of Clergy, a tender tale of a tragic interracial love affair, In the Rukh, the first appearance of Mowgli before The Jungle Book. The rest of the stories are set in Edwardian and early 20th C. Britain. There’s the pathetically touching semi-autobiographical Baa Baa Black Sheep about the cruelty of sending small children away from their parents to school in England. My Son’s Wife, a very modern feeling story of an urban sophisticate seduced by the conservative pleasures of the countryside. It could almost be the inspiration of Blur’s Country House. And then there’s A Madonna of the Trenches, a very moving story of shell-shock and ghosts set in the trenches of WWI, where of course Kipling’s son lost his life. Sometime the Victorian wordiness gets a little tiring, and I gave up on one story, written in 19th C. soldier’s slang, as just too much like hard work. But when Kipling’s good he’s very good and on the whole I thoroughly enjoyed this volume.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Who We Are And How We Got Here</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-10-20-reich-who/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-10-20-reich-who/</guid><description>&lt;p>The book describes the revolution currently taking place in archeology thanks to the technology of ancient DNA sampling. It reveals a rich pattern of human dispersal and mixing over the past 100,000 years. In the very distant past it shows that there was interbreeding with Neaderthals and Denisovans, making us non-Africans something of a hybrid. There’s even some suggestion that Eurasian features like lighter skin might be inherited from them. In the more recent past it clears up some archeological disputes about whether cultural change in the archeological record is due to copying or population movement. It seems it’s almost always the latter. Also differences in Y-chromosome and mitochondrial DNA ancestry shows that in many cases males from the incoming population mated with females from the existing one. This is especially true of the Yamnaya people of the central European steppe who spread into northern Europe and South Asia around 4,000 years ago bringing indo-European languages, horses, and the wheel. It really is incredible to think of all the people struggling to survive over millennium, moving from place to place and fighting each other for dominance. How we are all the descents of a long line of survivors. Reich writes very well. It’s a very practical book that lays out the discoveries in a matter-of-fact style. He’s obviously very touchy about any association with theories of racial superiority, and explains at length how his discoveries do not support some of the more lurid online claims made about them. I thought his appeal to liberal ideas about individual equality regardless of one’s genetic inheritance was very good, and an excellent antidote to both right-wing racial supremacists and woke identity politics. This is a very exciting field. Reich describes how we might soon see a complete historical atlas of human movement and evolution. I expect he’ll have to write another book in a few years time with the updates.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Fire of the Dragon</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-06-16-williams-fire/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-06-16-williams-fire/</guid><description>&lt;p>What an excellent overview of China’s evolution into the planet’s prime threat to peace. Williams’ obviously has an agenda, and that’s to demonstrate that the era of engagement with China is over, and the world needs to urgently move to containment. In his telling we are already in a new cold war, and the sooner the West wakes up to that fact the safer we’ll be. What’s obvious throughout is how stupidly counterproductive China’s “wolf warrior” diplomacy has been. In short order they’ve alienated most of the world against them through bullying and arrogance. How not to make friends and influence people! The book is very good on how China’s aggressive and confrontational behaviour plays out in different parts of the world, from the Himalayas to the South China Sea, but most dramatically in the Taiwan Straight. William’s thinks we’re in a similar situation to Germany’s rise before WWI. It’s all quite scary and one very much hopes that cooler heads prevail in Beijing and we’re really heading for another global conflict.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How Music Works</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-05-31-byrne-music/</link><pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-05-31-byrne-music/</guid><description>&lt;p>A rather hit-and-miss book. Some sections were very interesting. I especially enjoyed the ones about how you get paid in the music business, or rather how it worked in the late 20th C. and how to “make a scene”. Some excellent interesting reflections on how the scene around CBGBs evolved in the late 70s and early 80s. Also very good were his personal reflections on making Talking Heads albums and taking them on tour, and the thought process behind them. I’m not a huge fan of Talking Heads, I always found the music rather repetitive and uninteresting, although there’s no doubt that David Byrne is a unique and talented vocalist and lyricist. It’s often more “performance art” than music as such, if that makes any sense? Unfortunately much of the book was just random philosophical musing that I find quite irritating. The last chapter, a riff on what the essence of music really is, was especially waffly and I ended up skimming over most of it. So some very good bits, but could have done with some heavy editing.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Extremely Online</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-05-06-lorenz-online/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-05-06-lorenz-online/</guid><description>&lt;p>It’s an excellent overview of the first quarter century of social media, from the early days of blogging in the 90’s through MySpace, then Twitter and Facebook, and finally onto TikTok. Fascinating because it’s also a personal history. I was a D-list tech blogger in the 2000s and 2010s, and an early and enthusiastic user of Twitter. Also my main source of entertainment has been YouTube for at least the last 15 years. The only big trend I seem to have missed is TikTok, but I see the effect of that secondhand through Yuna, who is glued to it for several hours a day. Lorenz is very good about the “creator economy” and the way it’s evolved to where it now rivals traditional media. She illustrates this with some lively potted biographies of chosen creators. She gives a balanced view of both the good, the bad, the excesses, and the burnout, but is occasionally rather US-progressive in her attitudes, blaming the relatively poorer showing of black creators/influencers as the result of deliberate “exploitation” rather than simple market forces. But that’s a minor gripe; overall, very well written and researched and an easy and enjoyable read.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Civilization</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-04-23-clarke-civ/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-04-23-clarke-civ/</guid><description>&lt;p>It’s been a very enlightening and entertaining read. Although he says it’s about western civilization in the broadest sense, it’s more accurately a history of art. Clarke knows his art and has very strong opinions about it. There’s no post-modern revisionism here; no doubts at all that western culture is the best. I found it quite charming and refreshing. Unfortunately he’s also got strong opinions about things he doesn’t know much about at all, such as science, technology, politics, and economics, and his observations on them are all a bit “man in pub”. It’s made even more ridiculous by the book being over 55 years old, and all his pronouncements about the cultural wasteland of the late 60’s made rather comic in the light of our current appraisal; that it was something of a cultural flowering. The art is wonderful though, and his descriptions and placement of the various famous artists in their place and period makes it a very good overview of 1500 years of European culture. I learnt a lot. The beautiful Folio binding and printing made it a tactile pleasure to read&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The BBC</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-04-06-hendy-bbc/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-04-06-hendy-bbc/</guid><description>&lt;p>An excellent and very well written account of how the BBC has grown and evolved over the last 100 years. I especially liked the early chapters about its foundation in the early 20’s following WWI and how it firmly established its reputation as the gold standard in news and reporting during WWII. A constant thread are the battles to stay independent of government and retain balance in news reporting, when it’s the government that sets the licence fee and thus the BBC’s budget. Also good on the constant push and pull between entertainment and popularity verses it’s mission to educate and improve. It ended on a rather depressing note with the horrible scandal of Jimmy Savile, and the controversy over the Blair government’s dodgy dossier - I don’t think either Blair or Alistair Cambell have every correctly atoned for that appalling chapter. I feel a bit guilty now about my own anti-BBC prejudices that I held for a long while.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Abroad In Japan</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-02-29-broad-japan/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-02-29-broad-japan/</guid><description>&lt;p>The tale of a JET program participant dumped into very rural Yamagata straight from university in the UK, and then over the next ten years succeeding as the biggest Japan YouTuber. It’s a great story with lots of quirky characters on the way; a chain smoking anglophile, a peacenik teacher, a random drunken night with a girl from Taiwan. He’s a very engaging, self depreciating, narrator. It’s definitely at its best at the beginning describing his JET years and then reads as if he’d got a little bored of writing towards the end. As a former JET myself it was a very familiar story, and the fact that he’d settled in Sendai made it even more poignant. For the first time in two decades I found myself thinking how nice it would be to travel to Japan again.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Blue Arena</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-02-04-spurdle-blue/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2024-02-04-spurdle-blue/</guid><description>&lt;p>What an epic tale! Bob Spurdle joined the Royal New Zeeland Air Force at the beginning of WWII and was immediately put on a boat to the UK and into the battle of Britain flying a Spitfire. He was a member of Sailor Malan’s famous squadron all through the battle and into 1941. He then took a job as a rocket catapult launched convoy fighter pilot on a couple of trips across the Atlantic, but managed to avoid action both times. Back in the UK he had a period as a recon pilot flying Spitfires over the French coast, but then return to the NZ and on to the Solomon Islands where he took part in the Guadalcanal battle. Very critical of the way the RNZAF was run, he returned the UK and became squadron leader flying the brand new Tempest during the D-Day landing and advance through France. If all this wasn’t enough, at the end of the war he volunteered as forward fighter director with the army and entered Germany in a tank. Many scenes of heartache as close friends perished, and disgust at the wonton destruction of war, but at the same time a cold blooded killer himself, interspersed with much humour and the joy of flying. Strong opinions about the various organisations he served (the RAF superb, the RNAZF woeful, the USAAF big and stupid - with disturbing tales of friendly fire) and the planes he flew (Spitfire and Tempest superb, the Hurricane an old crate, and the P40 a brick). It’s quite astonishing that he survived it all. He settled down after the war to life of business back at home in NZ and never flew a plane again. Engagingly written and very moving in places, an extraordinary tale that needed no embellishment. I thoroughly enjoyed it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Decadent Herbs</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2020-09-16-the-decadent-herbs/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2020-09-16-the-decadent-herbs/</guid><description>&lt;p>It was 1985, I was twenty years old and just back from nine months volunteering in India. I&amp;rsquo;d decided not to go to university, but instead to try my luck as a rock star, all I needed was a band.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The OwlBadger Guide to Yes</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-12-29-yes-3/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-12-29-yes-3/</guid><description>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-19-yes-1/">Part 1. Introduction and Early Albums&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-31-yes-2/">Part 2. Early Classic Period&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Part 3. Late Classic Period &lt;em>which you are now reading&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This is the third part of the Owlbadger guide to Yes. It covers, what I’m calling their ‘late classic period’, the albums: Tales From Topographic Oceans, Relayer, and Going For The One. This period is far more patchy in terms of quality than the &amp;rsquo;early classic period&amp;rsquo;, but features two Yes masterpieces that cannot be missed and much other music that any Yes fan will enjoy.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The OwlBadger Guide to Yes</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-31-yes-2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-31-yes-2/</guid><description>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-19-yes-1/">Part 1. Introduction and Early Albums&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Part 2. Early Classic Period &lt;em>which you are now reading&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-12-29-yes-3/">Part 3. Late Classic Period&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This is the second part of the Owlbadger guide to Yes. It covers, what I’m calling their ‘early classic period’, the albums: The Yes Album, Fragile, Close to the Edge and Yessongs. This is when the band produced much of their best work. The output of these albums is consistently excellent, especially compared with the more patchy ‘late classic’ period that we will be looking at next.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The OwlBadger Guide to Yes</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-19-yes-1/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-19-yes-1/</guid><description>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Part 1. Introduction and Early Albums &lt;em>which you are now reading&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-10-31-yes-2/">Part 2. Early Classic Period&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://owlbadger.com/posts/2019-12-29-yes-3/">Part 3. Late Classic Period&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This is the first in a series of Owlbadger guides, where we look at the work of one band or artist with a critical and opinionated eye. The idea is that someone unfamiliar with their work has an insight into where to start, what to spend time on and, more importantly, what to ignore; this is information that’s difficult to glean from an impartial source such as Wikipedia and is especially important with a band such as Yes, with a career spanning decades and an output that ranges dramatically in style and quality. There’s the added complication that some of their most commercially successful work is music that Owlbadger fans will heartily dislike. It’s easy to be mislead into thinking that Yes are simply awful 80’s MOR if all you’ve heard is ‘Owner of a Lonely Heart’, and that would be a great shame because, as I hope to show, Yes music from their early to mid 70’s era is one of the most glorious artifacts of the golden age of rock.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Awaken My Love!</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-07-09-awaken-my-love/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-07-09-awaken-my-love/</guid><description>&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Awaken, My Love!&amp;rdquo; is the 2016 studio album by Donald Glover, under his stage name Childish Gambino. A modern take on 70’s psychedelic funk and somewhat of a Prince tribute, it manages to combine crowd pleasing melodies with some quite messy left-field experimentation making it one of the more interesting records of the last few years.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Aristocrats</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-05-23-the-aristocrats/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-05-23-the-aristocrats/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is the 2011 self named debut album of instrumental supergroup The Aristocrats. A textbook exercise in instrumental rock. No overdubs, just virtuoso guitar, bass and drums playing fusion infused rock.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Flying Microtonal Banana</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-05-04-fmb/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-05-04-fmb/</guid><description>&lt;p>Flying Microtonal Banana is the ninth studio album by Melbourne psych rockers King Gizzard and the Lizard Wizard. Released in 2017 as part of their five albums in one year project, it’s a psychedelic masterpiece of driving rhythms and exotic eastern melodies.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Dojo</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-04-28-dojo/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-04-28-dojo/</guid><description>&lt;p>Dojo is the debut album by Jouis, Brighton based graduates of the local BIMM music school (the name is a French word that translates roughly to &amp;ldquo;High enjoyment&amp;rdquo;, apparently). A quintet when the album was recorded in 2015, and now a trio. It is a wholly undiscovered gem of a record, full of immersive, laid back, progressive vibes, and probably my favorite album of 2016.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Do Hollywood</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-04-25-do-hollywood/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2018-04-25-do-hollywood/</guid><description>&lt;p>Released in October 2016, this is the debut album by the Lemon Twigs. The creation of the teenage D’Addario brothers, Brian and Michael, it’s a work of quite astonishing precociousness.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Seal St. Lawrence</title><link>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2012-01-06-seal-st-lawrence/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://owlbadger.com/posts/2012-01-06-seal-st-lawrence/</guid><description>&lt;p>Seal St. Lawrence was my primary school, a tiny church of England school attached to the parish church.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Both were built in 1865 by Horace Wilkinson to commemorate his daughter. The building itself looked like a large victorian house facing a tarmac playground. Opposite the school building was a world war two air raid shelter. I vaguely remember it being used for storage. Around the back of the building was a garden which we were expressly forbidden to enter. Across the road was some woodland and then the sports field. We were allowed to play in the woodland during the lunchtime break, it seemed huge to me as a small boy. I remember kicking large mounds of fallen leaves around and endless games of British Bulldog. The playing fields had a football pitch with a running track around it and there were some apparatus on the far side including a frame with ropes, that I never managed to climb to the top of.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>